<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The protestants and Iesuites vp in armes in Gulicke-land Also, a true and wonderfull relation of a Dutch maiden (called Eue Fliegen of Meurs in the county of Meurs) who being now (this present yeare) 36 yeares of age, hath fasted for the space of 14 yeares, confirmed by the testimony of persons, both honourable and worshipfull, (as well English, as Dutch. Truely translatedi [sic] according to the Dutch coppy</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114340</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849566</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14721</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14721)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1528:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The protestants and Iesuites vp in armes in Gulicke-land Also, a true and wonderfull relation of a Dutch maiden (called Eue Fliegen of Meurs in the county of Meurs) who being now (this present yeare) 36 yeares of age, hath fasted for the space of 14 yeares, confirmed by the testimony of persons, both honourable and worshipfull, (as well English, as Dutch. Truely translatedi [sic] according to the Dutch coppy</title>
                  <author>Wood, T., fl. 1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By N. Okes] for Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by T. Wood.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fliegen, Eve, b. 1574 or 5 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Curiosities and wonders --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jülich (Germany) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14721:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Proteſtants and Ieſuites vp in Armes in Gulicke-land.</p>
            <p>Alſo, A true and wonderfull relation of a Dutch mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den (called <hi>Eue Fliegen</hi> of <hi>Meurs</hi> in the Country of <hi>Meurs</hi>) who being now (this preſent yeare) 36 yeares of age, hath faſted for the ſpace of 14 yeares, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the teſtimony of perſons, both Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and worſhipfull, (as well Engliſh, as Dutch.</p>
            <p>Truely tranſlated according to the Dutch Coppy.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of woman holding flower</figDesc>
               <head>EVA VLIEGE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:14721:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14721:2"/>
            <head>Laus Deo this 27 of Iuly Anno 1611 ſtilo magnae Brytanniae. The Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Brother: many hearty commendations, &amp;c. I haue ſent vnto you the picture and liuely deſcription of a Dutch maiden, drawn out of Dutch colours, &amp; put into Engliſh. The Dutch coppy comes along with it, which I haue tranſlated, as well to giue you teſtimony of my brotherly affection towards you, as to haue my Countreymen in <hi>England</hi> acquainted with ſo miraculous a power of Gods worke on ſo weake a creature, therby the more to magnifie his glory. If the newes of this be not as yet come to <hi>London,</hi> I wiſh you to ſend it to the Preſſe. It is not to be doubted but that a relation ſo freſh and vn-common, wil be acceptable to our Nation, to whom Newes are moſt welcome I know. To confirme the truth hereof, my Lord Generall, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noble Gentlemen, are worthy witneſſes, who both know this maiden, &amp; haue ſeene her. The report is new and lately publiſhed: If it had bin poſſible to haue gotten meanes (by a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14721:3"/>
meſſenger) ſooner to haue ſent it to you, it had ſooner come to your hands. But as it is, I pray receiue it, &amp; with it, a ſecond Newes, as freſh in the mouthes of all men, and fuller of conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by reaſon of an expected Euent thereof, to breake into a warres. And that is in <hi>Aken,</hi> within a dozen miles of <hi>Gulicke:</hi> which I pray you likewiſe to publiſh to the common view.</p>
            <div type="text">
               <head>The Dutch Coppy of the relation of Eue Fliegen of Meurs in the County of Meurs, a maiden (now aged 36 yeares) who hath neither eate nor drunke, any manner of Suſtenance, by the ſpace of 14 yeares, tranſlated into Engliſh as followeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Omnipotent Creator of the world, hath not in times paſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed the glory of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, in his wonderfull compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, framing and preſenting to the eye of Man all ſorts of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, both in heauen, earth, and the waters: But euen now at this day, is the ſame his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous hand working ſtill. Amongſt infinite numbers of which his excellent peeces, able to bold man in aſtoniſhment, this of a Maiden is well worthy of admiration, of whom (becauſe the true body and ſhape cannot in ſubſtance bee ſent vp and downe the world) this picture or counterfeit (ſo neere as words can
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14721:3"/>
expreſſe her) ſhewes her drawne to the life.</p>
               <p>This Maiden (by name <hi>Eue Fliegen</hi>) liues at this preſent within the towne of <hi>Meurs,</hi> ſhe was borne in the yeare of our Lord 1575, within a little of that towne at a place called <hi>Fliegen-houſe,</hi> wherupon ſhe takes her name: of meane and very poore parents. So that in her yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dayes (they being not able better to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine her) ſhe was compelled to keepe ſwine for the country people, enduring (by that hard courſe of life) the bitterneſſe of much hunger, as ſhe her ſelfe confeſſeth.</p>
               <p>Liuing in this extremity of miſery, ſhe often (ſo well as ſhe could, ſeeing no other wayes nor hope of comfort) made earneſt prayers to God, that he would take pitty of her wretchednes, and relieue her, from that daily hunger, by which her body was tormented &amp; conſumed: her prayers were heard, according to her requeſt: And ſuch compaſſion tooke the Almighty of her miſeries that in the yeare 1594, her deſire of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which in former times ſhe had grew to be faint, &amp; very ſmall. Inſomuch that euery 2, 3 &amp; 4 daies, ſhe tooke little ſuſtenance or none at all. From the 4 day ſhe began voluntarily to faſt til the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 day &amp; ſo did forbeare, or rather had no ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke to meate, the ſpace of fourteene dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which abſtene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hers grew in the end end to ſuch a cuſtome, that ſhee vtterly refuſed the taſt either of meate or drinke, and in that manner hath her body (by Gods prouidence) bene preſerued euer ſince the yeare of our Lord
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14721:4"/>
1597 to this preſent yeare 1611 (being full 14 yeares) This ſtrange wonder continuing thus long, drew not onely many people to ſee her, but alſo many tryals to be put vpon her, amongſt which, this was one, In the yeare 1599, the Noble Counteſſe of <hi>Meurs</hi> with her waiting Gentlewoman, hauing brought this <hi>Eue Flei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> into a garden, with much importunity to haue her eate ſomewhat, ſo preuailed that ſhee plucked a cherry and taſted it, and had no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner eaten it downe, but that the Lady with her ſeruants were in feare ſhee would there preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue dyed, ſhee fell into ſo ſodaine and violent paſſion of an extreme ſickeneſſe: in the which ſhe continued a long time, but in the end with much ado recouered her health. Which a yeare after the ſaid <hi>Eue</hi> falling againe into a greater ſickenes, it was held fit (by the opinion of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) to haue her drinke a ſpoonefull or two of the thin whey, which comes from Buttermilke, being ſodden: ſhee made offer to taſt it, but could by no meanes take it downe. At another time of ſicknes, ſhee her ſelfe thought ſhe could ſup the broth of a chicken, but no more then a ſpoonefull being offered to her, ſhee fell into a more extreme fit of ſickenes then before, ſo that finding her body afflicted by theſe tryals, ſhee vtterly abandoned the vſe of any food, or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, by the full ſpace now of 14 yeares. In all which time, through no diſpoſition of the ſeaſon or time of the yeare, hath ſhee bene ſeene or knowne either to complaine of thirſt or hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14721:4"/>
yet vntill her age of 20 or 22 yeares, ſhee tooke her food (where by her labour or other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meanes it could be gotten) as other people commonly vſe to do.</p>
               <p>This her forbearance to take the due nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſhould maintaine life, hath brought her body to a weaknes, and her face to an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding palenes.</p>
               <p>She ſaith that euery ſecond day an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding cleere light ſhineth round about her body; the common light or brightnes of the day, being nothing comparable to it: which light when ſhe beholdeth and (as ſhe ſaith) feeleth ſhining vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, ſhe hath likewiſe a feeling on her tongue of a ſtrange and extraordinary delicate ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the moiſture of which ſtrengthens her (to her ſeeming) for her eies can behold no other thing but only that perfect and vnuſuall light.</p>
               <p>The Preacher of <hi>Meurs</hi> (by name, <hi>Conradus Felthnijſen</hi>) could not along time be perſwaded that this was truth, which hee heard reported of this maiden: to giue therefore not onely content to himſelfe, but ſatisfaction in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to others his friends who were of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe likewiſe, he tooke the ſaid <hi>Eue</hi> (being come to heare the euening Sermon) home with him to his owne houſe, &amp; there kept her in a chamber by the ſpace of 13 daies, watched day and night by ſundry other perſons his friends, candles burning euery night, and ſhe neuer being ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be alone without company the ſpace of one minute, in all which time ſhee neuer taſted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14721:5"/>
foode, and (at the end of 13 daies and nights) being demanded whether ſhe where then either hungry or thirſty, ſhe anſwered no: ſo that the Preacher now hauing by the experience of his owne eyes, found out that which he could not before beleeue, is now inforced with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to acknowledge to be true. To whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, a thouſand perſons (both honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and of other condition) can witneſſe, and there is ſhe liuing at this day, in the towne of <hi>Meurs</hi> to be ſeene, and ſpoken with daily and hourely, &amp; her manner of liuing being obſerued with the narroweſt eyes, &amp; ſeuereſt circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that it is impoſſible, ſhe ſhould be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſter or deluder: and the better to confirme the truth of this, a worthy Magiſtrate of the ſame towne hath giuen liberall and ample approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to certaine Citties, &amp; to ſeuerall perſons of worth, with his certificate and the ſeale of the towne thereunto annexed: if all theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of her, cannot perſwade and win credit to our report, the maiden (of whom it is made) is yet to be ſeene, in the towne of <hi>Meurs.</hi> Nor ſhall it be amiſſe, the better to ſtrengthen this ſhort diſcourſe, to ſet downe in a few lines more what ſome hiſtories of our preſent times do mention of perſons who in the like manner haue faſted long (beyond the ordinary ſtrength &amp; cuſtome of mans body) and liued (as this maiden does now) without eating.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Franciſcus Citeſius</hi> (Doctor in the vniuerſity at <hi>Poitiers</hi>) witneſſeth (in his booke written in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14721:5"/>
Lattine &amp; imprinted at <hi>Montpellier</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1602) that for certaine yeares, one <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Colberghen</hi> liued in <hi>Spires</hi> 7 yeares together, without meate or drinke. Alſo within the town of <hi>Conflans</hi> in <hi>France</hi> lying vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the borders of <hi>Limoſin</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riuer <hi>Vien,</hi> A Smith (by name, <hi>Iohn Balam</hi>) begot of his wife <hi>(Lucrece Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belle)</hi> in the yeare 1588, a daughter named <hi>Ione Balam,</hi> who for the ſpace of two yeares, did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate or drinke, in publication of which wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that famous and eloquent Doctor, <hi>Iacobus Viuerius</hi> wrote certaine verſes, which are thus Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How many wonders great before our eies appeares,</l>
                     <l>Whereof no reaſon firme to you can ſhewed be.</l>
                     <l>Behold, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in health, indures at womans yeares</l>
                     <l>Twiſe a moneths long to faſt, for ſuſtenance none takes ſhe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Lords and neighbours there, to her had good regard,</l>
                     <l>That dwelt in <hi>Conflans</hi> towne, on that Vieniſh fare.</l>
                     <l>No meate no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> drinke in all that time ſo long ſhe mard,</l>
                     <l>Her throate ſo narrow was, her victuals ſhe did ſpare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Full ſtrange it was to ſee, her belly was ſo flat,</l>
                     <l>The paſſages were ſhut, no entrance there was found,</l>
                     <l>She voyded nothing forth, nothing at all ſhe ate,</l>
                     <l>Her priuy parts were cleane, thence nothing fel to grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But yet ſhe ſpeakes, ſhe ſighs, ſhe goes, ſhe feeles I know,</l>
                     <l>Mine eies are witnes ſure, here of you need not doubt:</l>
                     <l>Which wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drous work doth teach, that nature here below</l>
                     <l>By God alone is rul'd, who gouernes all about.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To whom all things that were, or euer yet ſhall be,</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtoope their lofty tops, their heads alſo muſt bend,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe wiſdom, might &amp; power, ô man doth teach to thee</l>
                     <l>To praiſe his name for aye: And ſo I make an end.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14721:6"/>
                  <hi>Ouer the picture of the maiden in the Dutch Coppy, ſtood theſe Lattine verſes, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Meurſae haec (quam Cernis) decies tor, ſex<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> peregit</l>
                  <l>Annos, bis ſeptem prorſus non veſcitur Annis.</l>
                  <l>Nec potat, ſic ſola ſedet, ſic pallida vitam</l>
                  <l>Ducit, &amp; exigni ſe oblectat floribus Horti.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus Engliſhed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>This Maid (of <hi>Meurs</hi>) hath thirty ſixe yeare ſpent.</l>
                  <l>Fourteene of which ſhe tooke no nouriſhment,</l>
                  <l>Thus pale and wan ſhee ſits (ſad and alone)</l>
                  <l>A garden is all ſhe loues to looke vpon.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Brother, if you call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance my former letters (written vnto you about the beginning of September 1605) you ſhall find in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a report of this Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Meurs,</hi> who at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time had faſted but eight yeares: which report I know you very ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, and as I thinke, thought it fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vntrue: But before that time, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince, her manner of liuing hath beene ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly looked into, that I am now my ſelfe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly perſwaded to beleeue it, becauſe not onely I, but thouſands beſides, haue ſeene her, &amp; can teſtify with mee. None of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> nor any Noblemen or Gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> trauelling neere that way, but haue bene eye-witneſſes of what I write to you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her many at this preſent in the Engliſh Court haue ſeene her. His excellency <hi>(Graue Maurice)</hi> who is Earle of <hi>Meurs,</hi> neuer commeth into the Towne, but he makes her one of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14721:6"/>
gueſts, yet ſhe eateth noting at all. Thus much of this wonder. Now for <hi>Gulicke-newes.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="news">
               <head>The Proteſtants and Ieſuites vp in Armes in Gulicke-land.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T <hi>Aken,</hi> a great Towne (where the Crowne of the Empire is kept) ſtanding within 12 miles of <hi>Gulicke,</hi> in <hi>Gulicke-land</hi> did this quarrell begin, vpon the occaſion following.</p>
               <p>Since the taking of <hi>Gulick,</hi> that the land was gouerned by a Proteſtant Prince, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants preſumed (as well they might) to haue more liberty then they had wont, and to go to heare Sermons a mile or two out of the towne (yet in moſt Townes in <hi>Cleue-land</hi> they vſe to preach in Churches) The Ieſuites taking note of this, and the Magiſtrates being Papiſts &amp; fauourers of their owne religion, conſulted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether how to ſtop this tide and paſſage of the Proteſtants from ſwelling to a greater ſtreame &amp; thereupon ſuddenly apprehended as many of the Proteſtants that had bene at the Sermons as they could poſſible lay hands vpon: Great fines being ſet vpon ſome, and the reſt (whoſe number were not few) appointed to be baniſhed. Which ſeuerity &amp; cruell doome was borne with patience ſo long, that out of <hi>Aken</hi> were drawne into baniſhment 300 families at leaſt, and that vpon the 13 day of Iune (now laſt paſt) there were to bee ſent from thence into the like miſery and exile a great number more,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14721:7"/>
The ſight of which, ſtriking into the hearts of the common Burgeſſes of the towne, &amp; mouing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they reſolued to go altogether to the Town-hall, to haue their poore country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, with their wiues and children ſtaied: at their intreaty, and humble interceſſion, they did ſo, as they reſolued, and came to the place where their Magiſtrates were aſſembled: But no praiers, no teares, no intreaty could preuaile, but all were by the Magiſtrates ſharpely char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and commanded to depart peaceably home to their houſes: for they knew well enough what belonged to their places, to the ſtate of towne, and what was to be done.</p>
               <p>But a number of people (both Proteſtants and Papiſts) in a mixed aſſembly being gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, before the Towne-hall, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts expecting the euent of this new buſines, the Proteſtants lamenting the baniſhment &amp; departure of their friends, kindſ-folkes, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, and ſeeing no hope to find any mercy at the Magiſtrats hands, ſome (amongſt the reſt) burſt out into paſſionate expoſtulations, crying (out of their true pitty, ſorrow, and deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.) Is there no remedie, no helping ſtrong hand that can, or that dares caſt off a burthen ſo heauy, and ſo intollerable as this? Muſt we behold our fathers, our ſonnes, our brethren, wiues, ſiſters &amp; acquaintance, driuen thus like out-caſts into forreine and vnknowne countries (out of our natiue land) onely for hearing the word of God truly preached amongſt vs. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14721:7"/>
is there none ſo valiant to ſtep forth and defend them and vs from this miſerable and tyranous bondage? Can we fight for the ſame cauſe (O you faint-harted Dutch nation) againſt proud forreine people, keeping them out at the ſwords point, and ſhall we not be able to maintaine our owne quarrell againſt our owne countrimen? Can our armes and our weapons, with which we haue wonne battailes, not now helpe our ſelues? no, no, replyed others, we the wretched and diſpiſed number of the Proteſtants are few, but the Ieſuits and Papiſts (our cruell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies) are many and ſtrong, Yet cryed others in what nobler, in what better quarrell can wee venture our liues, and, venturing ſo looſe them, then in defence of the Goſpell, our country, our brethren, kindred, and friends? Wee are Gods Souldiers in ſo iuſt a warre, &amp; therefore why do we not arme our ſelues to maintaine his cauſe? Theſe and ſuch like ſpeeches, annimated the people, kindled manly fire in their boſomes, and ſo inflamed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that on a ſuddain, flying to their beſt defence and guard of ſafety, Arme, Arme, Arme, was cryed, euery one betooke him to his weapons, ſo that within one halfe hower, all the towne was filled with armed men, the wals giuing as much cauſe of terror to the country-faction as the ſtreetes did, becauſe they were as ſuddenly and as brauely manned too.</p>
               <p>The keyes of the gates being ſeized vpon, into the Proteſtants hands, an able and ſtout watch was preſently chooſen, and planted for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14721:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their better ſecurity: the old Magiſtrates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued and new put into their places, and (as it often happens in ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motions) nothing was left vndone, which the rage of people newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from feare, and hauing now the bridle of gouernment to themſelues, had will to execute, ſo that all priſons were ſet open, &amp; all priſoners at liberty to ſtrengthen their ſide, and fight for them, becauſe they were now rather to do then to deliberate: to the Ieſuites Cloiſters they went, where they ſlew ſome, tooke other priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp; thoſe who eſcaped beſt went away with much danger of their liues: the Cloiſters were defaced, Altars throwne downe, Images bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in peeces, &amp; after many violent-outrages, in the end the towne of <hi>Aken</hi> was ſurpriſed and made theirs. And now (comming to capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) the Papiſts would be content to ſuffer the Proteſtants to Preach without the towne: but the Proteſtants on the contrary part, will not now ſuffer them to exerciſe their Maſſe within the Towne, but thruſt them out of the gate.</p>
               <p>This quarrell hanging yet in a doubtfull bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, is to be decided by the Duke of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> (prince of that country) now beeing in high <hi>Germany.</hi> What hereafter enſues vpon it I ſhall (deere broth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r) God willing acquaint you in writing, and be ſorry, if this ſhort relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our <hi>Gulicks</hi> ſeruice, proue not delightfull to your ſelfe, or to any of your friends and my Countrimen, that may read happily the ſame. I did not more enlarge it. Farewell from <hi>Vtrecht.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
